Chris Anderson: We had Edward Snowden here
كريس اندرسون: كان لدينا ادوارد سنودين هنا
a couple days ago,
قبل عده ايام,
and this is response time.
والان هو وقت الرد.
And several of you have written to me
الكثيرون منكم كتبوا لي
with questions to ask our guest here from the NSA.
اسئله لتقديمها الى ضيفنا هنا اليوم من وكاله الامن القومي الامريكيه (الوكاله)
So Richard Ledgett is the 15th deputy director
لذا ريتشارد ليدجيت هو نائب المدير
of the National Security Agency,
لوكاله الامن القومي الامريكيه
and he's a senior civilian officer there,
وهو ضابط مدني كبير هناك
acts as its chief operating officer,
و يعمل كمدير العمليات في الوكاله ,
guiding strategies, setting internal policies,
موجها الاستراتيجيات و واضعا السياسات ,
and serving as the principal advisor to the director.
ويعمل كمستشار اساسي للمدير .
And all being well,
وهكذا ,
welcome, Rick Ledgett, to TED.
مرحبا , ريتشارد ليدجيت , في تيد
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Richard Ledgett: I'm really thankful for the opportunity to talk to folks here.
ريتشارد ليدجيت: انا شاكر للفرصه للتحدث مع الجمهور هنا ,
I look forward to the conversation,
واتطلع قدما لهذا الحوار,
so thanks for arranging for that.
شكرا لمنحي هذه الفرصه,
CA: Thank you, Rick.
كريس: شكرا , ريتشارد.
We appreciate you joining us.
ممتنون لمشاركتك معنا.
It's certainly quite a strong statement
انه فعل قوي بلا شك ,
that the NSA is willing to reach out
ان (الوكاله) ترغب في ان تتواصل معنا
and show a more open face here.
و تظهر وجها اكثر تعاونا هنا .
You saw, I think,
اعتقد انك شاهدت ,
the talk and interview that Edward Snowden
المحادثه و اللقاء مع ادوارد سنودين
gave here a couple days ago.
هنا قبل عده ايام .
What did you make of it?
ما هو رايك فيها ؟
RL: So I think it was interesting.
ريتشارد: اعتقد انها كانت مثيره للاهتمام ,
We didn't realize that he was going to show up there,
لم نكن نعلم انه سيظهر هنا ,
so kudos to you guys for arranging
لذا فالشكر لكم على تدبير
a nice surprise like that.
مفاجأه جيده مثل تلك المحادثه.
I think that, like a lot of the things
اعتقد , مثل معظم الاشياء
that have come out since Mr. Snowden
التي خرجت للعلن منذ قام السيد سنودين
started disclosing classified information,
بكشف معلومات سريه ,
there were some kernels of truth in there,
كانت هناك بضع حبات من الحقيقه فيها
but a lot of extrapolations and half-truths in there,
ولكن ايضا الكثير من الاستقراءات الخاطئه وانصاف الحقيقه,
and I'm interested in helping to address those.
وانا مهتم في المساعده على توضيح هذه الاخطاء.
I think this is a really important conversation
اعتقد ان هذه محادثه مهمه
that we're having in the United States
لنا في الولايات المتحده
and internationally,
والعالم,
and I think it is important and of import,
واعتقد انها مهمه و ذات اهميه,
and so given that, we need to have that be
وبالنظر الى ذلك , نحتاج الى ان يكون هذا الحوار العام
a fact-based conversation,
حوارا مبنيا على الحقائق ,
and we want to help make that happen.
ونحن نريد المساعده على تحقيق ذلك.
CA: So the question that a lot of people have here is,
كريس: السؤال الذي يريد الكثيرون هنا سؤاله هو ,
what do you make of Snowden's motivations
ما هو رأيك في دوافع سنودين
for doing what he did,
للقيام بما قام به
and did he have an alternative way that he could have gone?
وهل كانت لديه اي خيارات بديله ؟
RL: He absolutely did
ريتشارد: قطعا كانت لديه خيارات بديله
have alternative ways that he could have gone,
كانت هناك طرق اخرى كان بامكانه سلوكها
and I actually think that characterizing him
واعتقد ان وصفه
as a whistleblower
ككاشف تجاوزات
actually hurts legitimate whistleblowing activities.
يضر في الواقع نشاطات كشف التجاوزات الحقيقيه
So what if somebody who works in the NSA --
ماذا لو قام شخص يعمل في الوكاله --
and there are over 35,000 people who do.
وهناك اكثر من 35 الف شخص يعملون هنا
They're all great citizens.
وكلهم مواطنون جيدون.
They're just like your husbands, fathers, sisters,
انهم مثل ازواجكم , اباءكم , اخوانكم,
brothers, neighbors, nephews, friends and relatives,
اخوتكم, جيرانكم, اصدقائكم و اقاربكم,
all of whom are interested in doing the right thing
وكلهم مهتمون بالقيام بما هو صحيح
for their country
لبلدهم
and for our allies internationally,
و لحلفاءنا عالميا ,
and so there are a variety of venues to address
لذا هناك الكثير من الطرق يمكن سلوكها
if folks have a concern.
لو كان لهم بعض الملاحظات.
First off, there's their supervisor,
اولا , هناك المسؤول المباشر عنهم ,
and up through the supervisory chain
و صعودا عبر سلم المسؤولين
within their organization.
داخل منظوماتهم.
If folks aren't comfortable with that,
ان لم يكونو مرتاحين لذلك,
there are a number of inspectors general.
هناك العديد من المفتشين العموميين.
In the case of Mr. Snowden, he had the option
في حاله السيد سنودين , كان لديه الخيار
of the NSA inspector general,
للذهاب للمفتش العمومي لوكاله الامن القومي,
the Navy inspector general,
المفتش العمومي للبحريه,
the Pacific Command inspector general,
المفتش العمومي لقياده الاطلسي,
the Department of Defense inspector general,
المفتش العمومي لوزاره الدفاع,
and the intelligence community inspector general,
والمفتش العمومي للاستخبارات ,
any of whom would have both kept his concerns in classified channels
كلهم كانو سيحتفظون بشكواه في مسارات محميه
and been happy to address them.
و كانو سيكونون سعداء بحلها
(CA and RL speaking at once)
(كريس و ريتشارد يتحدثون في نفس الوقت)
He had the option to go to congressional committees,
كان لديه خيار الذهاب الى لجان الكونجرس,
and there are mechanisms to do that that are in place,
وهناك العديد من الطرق لفعل ذلك
and so he didn't do any of those things.
و هو لم يقم بفعل اي من هذه الاشياء .
CA: Now, you had said that
كريس: انت قلت الان ,
Ed Snowden had other avenues
ان ادوارد سنودين كانت لديه خيارات اخرى
for raising his concerns.
لنقل شكواه .
The comeback on that is a couple of things:
والرد على ذلك في بضع نقاط :
one, that he certainly believes that as a contractor,
واحد, انه يعتقد انه كمتعاقد ,
the avenues that would have been available to him as an employee weren't available,
لم تكن متوفره له الفرص التي تتوفر للموظفين ,
two, there's a track record of other whistleblowers,
اثنين, هناك تاريخ من كاشفي التجاوزات السابقين له ,
like [Thomas Andrews Drake] being treated
مثل (ثوماس اندرو دريك) تم التعامل معهم
pretty harshly, by some views,
بصوره قاسيه جدا , حسب بعض الاراء ,
and thirdly, what he was taking on
وثالثا, ان ما كان يتحدث عنه
was not one specific flaw that he'd discovered,
لم يكن خطأ واحدا محددا قام باكتشافه ,
but programs that had been approved
بل برامج تمت الموافقه عليها
by all three branches of government.
عن طريق الافرع الثلاث للحكومه.
I mean, in that circumstance,
اعني , في تلك الظروف
couldn't you argue that what he did
الا نستطيع القول ان ما قام به
was reasonable?
كان منطقيا؟
RL: No, I don't agree with that.
ريتشارد: لا , لا اوافق على ذلك .
I think that the —
اعتقد ان __
sorry, I'm getting feedback
اسف, اسمع صوتا
through the microphone there —
من خلال المايكرفون هناك __
the actions that he took were inappropriate
الافعال التي قام بها لم تكن مناسبه
because of the fact that he put people's lives at risk,
لانه وضع حيوات اشخاص في خطر ,
basically, in the long run,
ببساطه , على المدى الطويل,
and I know there's been a lot of talk
واعلم ان هناك الكثير من الاقاويل
in public by Mr. Snowden and some of the journalists
في الاعلام بواسطه السيد سنودين و بعض الصحفيين
that say that the things that have been disclosed
التي تقول ان الاشياء التي تم الكشف عنها
have not put national security and people at risk,
لم تضع الامن القومي و الناس في خطر
and that is categorically not true.
و هذا غير صحيح البته .
They actually do.
هم في الواقع وضعو الامن و حياه الناس في خطر
I think there's also an amazing arrogance
اعتقد كذلك ان هناك غرور مدهش
to the idea that he knows better than
في فكره انه يعلم افضل من
the framers of the Constitution
من واضعي الدستور
in how the government should be designed and work
في كيفيه تصميم و عمل الحكومه
for separation of powers
لفصل السلطات
and the fact that the executive and the legislative branch
و حقيقه ان الفرع التنفيذي و التشريعي
have to work together and they have checks and balances on each other,
يجب ان يعملو سويا و لديهم توازن فيما بينهم
and then the judicial branch,
وبعدها الفرع القضائي
which oversees the entire process.
والذي يشرف على كل العمليه
I think that's extremely arrogant on his part.
اعتقد ان هذا غرور كبير من جانبه.
CA: Can you give a specific example
كريس: هل يمكنك اعطاءنا مثالا محددا
of how he put people's lives at risk?
عن كيفيه وضعه لحياه الناس في خطر ؟
RL: Yeah, sure.
ريتشارد: نعم, بالتأكيد.
So the things that he's disclosed,
الاشياء التي قام بكشفها,
the capabilities,
المقدرات,
and the NSA is a capabilities-based organization,
و (الوكاله) هي منظمه مبنيه على المقدرات,
so when we have foreign intelligence targets,
لذا عندما يكون لدينا اهداف استخبارات اجنبيه,
legitimate things of interest --
اهداف مشروعه للبحث و التقصي--
like, terrorists is the iconic example,
مثل, الارهابيين كمثال واضح ,
but it includes things like human traffickers,
و تتضمن ايضا اشياء مثل المتاجرين بالبشر,
drug traffickers,
مهربي المخدرات,
people who are trying to build advanced weaponry, nuclear weapons,
جهات تحاول بناء اسلحه متطوره, اسلحه نوويه,
and build delivery systems for those,
و بناء انظمه اطلاق لهذه الاسلحه ,
and nation-states who might be executing aggression against their immediate neighbors,
و دول يمكن ان يحاولوا القيام بافعال عدائيه لجيرانهم المباشرين ,
which you may have some visibility
وقد تكون متابعا
into some of that that's going on right now,
لبعض من ذلك الذي يحدث الان ,
the capabilities are applied
لذا هذه المقدرات يتم تطبيقها
in very discrete and measured and controlled ways.
بوسائل سريه و مقاسه و محكمه .
So the unconstrained disclosure of those capabilities
لذا الكشف الغير محكوم عن هذه المقدرات
means that as adversaries see them
يعني ان الاعداء يمكن ان يروها
and recognize, "Hey, I might be vulnerable to this,"
و ينتبهو. "انظر , يمكن استعمال هذا ضدي",
they move away from that,
و بالتالي يبتعدون عن مواطن الخطر ,
and we have seen targets in terrorism,
ولقد رأينا اهداف ارهابيه ,
in the nation-state area,
و اهداف حكوميه ,
in smugglers of various types, and other folks
و اهداف تهريب متعدده , وغيرها من الاهداف ,
who have, because of the disclosures,
الذين , بسبب هذه الكشوفات ,
moved away from our ability
ابتعدوا عن مقدراتنا
to have insight into what they're doing.
في رصد ما يقومون به .
The net effect of that is that our people
والتأثير النهائي لهذا هو ان افرادنا
who are overseas in dangerous places,
الذين هم بالخارج في مواقع خطره
whether they're diplomats or military,
سواء كانوا دبلوماسيين او عسكريين ,
and our allies who are in similar situations,
و حلفاءنا الذين هم في مواقف مشابهه,
are at greater risk because we don't see
هم الان في خطر اكبر لاننا لا نرى
the threats that are coming their way.
الاخطار التي تحيق بهم .
CA: So that's a general response saying that
كريس: اذا هذا رد عام يقول
because of his revelations,
انه بسبب كشوفات سنودين ,
access that you had to certain types of information
فان مقدراتكم للوصول الى انواع محدده من المعلومات
has been shut down, has been closed down.
قد تضررت , تم ايقافها .
But the concern is that the nature of that access
ولكن القلق الاساسي هو ان طبيعه هذا الوصول للمعلومات
was not necessarily legitimate in the first place.
لم يكن بالاساس مشروعا في المقام الاول.
I mean, describe to us this Bullrun program
اعني , صف لنا مثلا برنامج "بولرون"
where it's alleged that the NSA
الذي تم فيه اتهام (الوكاله)
specifically weakened security
بانها تحديدا قامت باضعاف الامن الالكتروني
in order to get the type of access that you've spoken of.
من اجل الوصول الى هذا النوع من مقدرات الاختراق التي تكلمت عنها.
RL: So there are, when our
ريتشارد: طيب, عندما تقوم
legitimate foreign intelligence targets of the type that I described before,
الاهداف الاستخباريه الاجنبيه التي تحدثت عنها سابقا,
use the global telecommunications system
عندما تقوم هذه الاهداف باستعمال نظام الاتصال العالمي
as their communications methodology,
كوسيله اتصالهم الاساسيه,
and they do, because it's a great system,
وهم يقومون بذلك لانها وسيله اتصال جيده,
it's the most complex system ever devised by man,
انه النظام الاعقد الذي قام بصنعه انسان,
and it is a wonder,
نظام اعجوبه,
and lots of folks in the room there
والكثير من الحضور عندك في المؤتمر
are responsible for the creation
مسؤولون عن صنعه
and enhancement of that,
و تطويره ,
and it's just a wonderful thing.
و هو نظام رائع.
But it's also used by people who are
ولكن يتم استخدامه ايضا من قبل افراد
working against us and our allies.
يعملون ضدنا و ضد حلفاءنا .
And so if I'm going to pursue them,
لذا اذا اردت ملاحقتهم ,
I need to have the capability
يجب ان تكون لدي المقدرات
to go after them,
لمطاردتهم,
and again, the controls are in
وانبه, ان المسؤوليه في
how I apply that capability,
كيفيه استعمالي لهذه المقدرات التجسسيه ,
not that I have the capability itself.
وليس في كوني املك هذه المقدرات ام لا .
Otherwise, if we could make it so that
والا , ان كان بامكاننا ان نجعل
all the bad guys used one corner of the Internet,
كل الاشرار يستعملون ركنا من الانترنت ,
we could have a domain, badguy.com.
واسمينا موقعهم , الاشرار دوت كوم مثلا .
That would be awesome,
لكان هذا رائعا ,
and we could just concentrate all our efforts there.
وكان يمكن ان نركز كل جهودنا على هذا الموقع ,
That's not how it works.
ولكن الامور لا تجري هكذا .
They're trying to hide
انهم يحاولون الاختباء
from the government's ability
من مقدره الحكومه على
to isolate and interdict their actions,
عزلهم و منع نشاطهم ,
and so we have to swim in that same space.
لذا علينا السباحه كلنا في نفس المحيط.
But I will tell you this.
ولكن دعني اقول لك الاتي .
So NSA has two missions.
وكاله الامن القومي الامريكيه لديها مهمتين .
One is the Signals Intelligence mission
واحده هي التجسس
that we've unfortunately read so much about in the press.
التي لأاسف قرأنا الكثير عنها في الصحافه .
The other one is the Information Assurance mission,
والثانيه هي تأمين المعلومات ,
which is to protect the national security systems of the United States,
وتعني تأمين انظمه الامن القومي للولايات المتحده الامريكيه
and by that, that's things like
واعني بذلك اشياء مثل
the communications that the president uses,
الاتصالات التي يقوم بها الرئيس.
the communications that control our nuclear weapons,
انظمه الاتصال التي تتحكم في اسلحتنا النوويه ,
the communications that our military uses around the world,
انظمه الاتصال التي تستعملها قواتنا العسكريه في انحاء العالم ,
and the communications that we use with our allies,
و الاتصالات التي نقوم بها مع حلفاءنا ,
and that some of our allies themselves use.
و بعض انظمه الاتصالات التي يستعملها حلفاءنا انفسهم .
And so we make recommendations on standards to use,
لذا نقوم بعمل توصيات للمعايير الواجب استعمالها ,
and we use those same standards,
و نستعمل نفس هذه المعايير ,
and so we are invested
لذا نحن مستثمرون ومهتمون
in making sure that those communications
بالتأكد من ان انظمه الاتصال هذه
are secure for their intended purposes.
مؤمنه من اجل استعمالاتها المقصوده .
CA: But it sounds like what you're saying is that
كريس: ولكن يبدوا لي ان ما تقوله هو
when it comes to the Internet at large,
انه عندما يتعلق الامر بالانترنت عموما ,
any strategy is fair game
فان استعمال اي استراتيجيه امر مشروع
if it improves America's safety.
لو كانت تؤدي الى تحسين امن امريكا .
And I think this is partly where there is such
واعتقد ان هذا تحديدا هو السبب في وجود
a divide of opinion,
انقسام في الرأي,
that there's a lot of people in this room
ان هناك الكثيرون موجودون هنا
and around the world
و حول العالم
who think very differently about the Internet.
الذين يعتقدون في الانترنت بصوره مختلفه .
They think of it as a momentous
يعتبرون الانترنت شيئا اساسيا
invention of humanity,
اختراعا انسانيا
kind of on a par with the Gutenberg press, for example.
تقريبا في نفس مستوى آله الطباعه مثلا.
It's the bringer of knowledge to all.
الانترنت هو حامل المعرفه للجميع .
It's the connector of all.
الرابط بين كل الناس .
And it's viewed in those sort of idealistic terms.
يعني يتم النظر اليه بتلك النظره المثاليه.
And from that lens,
ومن هذا المنظور,
what the NSA has done is equivalent to
ما قامت به وكاله الامن القومي الامريكيه مساوي
the authorities back in Germany
لما قامت به السلطات النازيه الالمانيه
inserting some device into every printing press
من وضع اجهزه في المطابع
that would reveal which books people bought
يكشف اي الكتب قام الناس بشراءها
and what they read.
وما الذي قاموا بقراءته.
Can you understand that from that viewpoint,
هل يمكن تفهم ذلك من هذا المنظور ,
it feels outrageous?
يبدوا الامر مثيرا للحنق و الغضب ؟
RL: I do understand that, and I actually share the view of the utility of the Internet,
ريتشارد: انا اتفهم ذلك, وفي الواقع احمل نفس الفكره عن الانترنت
and I would argue it's bigger than the Internet.
و اضيف ان الامر اكبر من الانترنت.
It is a global telecommunications system.
انه نظام الاتصال العالمي .
The Internet is a big chunk of that, but there is a lot more.
الانترنت جزء كبير منه, ولكن هناك المزيد.
And I think that people have legitimate concerns
واعتقد ان الناس لهم مخاوف مشروعه
about the balance between transparency and secrecy.
حول التوازن بين الشفافيه و السريه.
That's sort of been couched as a balance
وقد تم نوعا ما صياغته كتوازن
between privacy and national security.
بين الخصوصيه و الامن القومي
I don't think that's the right framing.
ولا اعتقد ان هذا هو التأطير المناسب .
I think it really is transparency and secrecy.
اعتقد انها حقيقه هي الشفافيه و السريه.
And so that's the national and international conversation that we're having,
لذا هذه هي المحاوره القوميه و العالميه التي نقوم بها الان
and we want to participate in that, and want
ونحن نريد المشاركه فيها , و نريد
people to participate in it in an informed way.
للناس ان يشاركوا فيها بصوره متفهمه و عارفه بما يجري.
So there are things,
لذا هناك اشياء,
let me talk there a little bit more,
دعني اتحدث عن هذه النقطه قليلا,
there are things that we need to be transparent about:
هناك اشياء نحتاج لان نكون صريحين حولها:
our authorities, our processes,
مسؤولياتنا , طرق عملنا,
our oversight, who we are.
نطاق عملنا , من نحن.
We, NSA, have not done a good job of that,
نحن. وكاله الامن القومي الامريكيه, لم نقم عمل جيد بخصوص الشفافيه,
and I think that's part of the reason
واعتقد ان هذا جزء من السبب
that this has been so revelational
الذي جعل هذه الحادثه منتشره
and so sensational in the media.
و حساسه في الاعلام.
Nobody knew who we were. We were the No Such Agency, the Never Say Anything.
لا احد كان يدري عن ماهيتنا, كنا مجهولين, متكتمين.
There's takeoffs of our logo
هناك تقليعات من شعارنا ساخره
of an eagle with headphones on around it.
مثل نسر يضع سماعات حوله.
And so that's the public characterization.
لذا هذه هي صورتنا في الرأي العام.
And so we need to be more transparent about those things.
ويجب علينا ان نكون اكثر شفافيه حول هذه الامور.
What we don't need to be transparent about,
ما لا يجب ان نكون صريحين حوله,
because it's bad for the U.S.,
لانه يضر بنا في الولايات المتحده الامريكيه.,
it's bad for all those other countries that we work with
وهو يضر كل تلك الدول التي تعمل معنا
and that we help provide information
و التي نساعدها ونقدم لها المعلومات
that helps them secure themselves
التي تساعدهم في تأمين انفسهم
and their people,
و مواطنيهم,
it's bad to expose operations and capabilities
انه من السيئ كشف العمليات و المقدرات
in a way that allows the people that we're all working against,
في صوره تسمح للجهات التي نعمل ضدها كلنا ,
the generally recognized bad guys,
الاشرار بصوره عامه
to counter those.
ان يقاوموا هذه الجهود.
CA: But isn't it also bad to deal
كريس: ولكن اليس سيئا ايضا التعامل
a kind of body blow to the American companies
بصوره ضاره للشركات الامريكيه
that have essentially given the world
التي قدمت بصوره اساسيه للعالم
most of the Internet services that matter?
معظم خدمات الانترنت الهامه؟
RL: It is. It's really the companies are
ريتشارد: هذا صحيح, فعلا الشركات هي التي
in a tough position, as are we,
في وضع صعب , كما نحن,
because the companies,
لان الشركات,
we compel them to provide information,
نحن نشجعهم على تقديم المعلومات,
just like every other nation in the world does.
كما تفعل اي دوله اخرى.
Every industrialized nation in the world
اي دوله صناعيه في العالم
has a lawful intercept program
لديها نظام اعتراض قانوني
where they are requiring companies
يطالبون فيه الشركات
to provide them with information
باعطاءهم معلومات
that they need for their security,
يحتاجونها لامنهم,
and the companies that are involved
والشركات المشاركه في هذا الامر
have complied with those programs
قد تعاونت مع هذه البرامج
in the same way that they have to do
بنفس الطريقه التي يتعاونون فيها
when they're operating in Russia or the U.K.
عندما يعملون في روسيا او بريطانيا مثلا.
or China or India or France,
او الصين او الهند او فرنسا,
any country that you choose to name.
اي دوله تريد تسميتها.
And so the fact that these revelations
لذا حقيقه ان هذه الكشوفات
have been broadly characterized as
قد تم تشخيصها عموما بالمقوله
"you can't trust company A because
"لا يمكنك الثقه بالشركه أ مثلا لان
your privacy is suspect with them"
خصوصيتك مشكوك في سلامتها معهم"
is actually only accurate in the sense that
هي في الحقيقه دقيقه بنفس احساس الدقه
it's accurate with every other company in the world
في ان العباره صحيحه لكل شركه في العالم
that deals with any of those countries in the world.
تتعامل مع اي من هذه الدول في العالم.
And so it's being picked up by people
لذا فانه يتم اخذ هذا التعميم من قبل الناس
as a marketing advantage,
كسياسه تسويق تفضيليه
and it's being marketed that way by several countries,
ويتم تسويقها بهذا الشكل في عده دول ,
including some of our allied countries,
بما في ذلك بعض الدول الحليفه لنا ,
where they are saying,
حيث يقولون,
"Hey, you can't trust the U.S.,
"انظر, لا يمكنك الثقه بالولايات المتحده الامريكيه.
but you can trust our telecom company,
ولكن يمكنك الثقه في شركتنا للاتصالات,
because we're safe."
لاننا آمنون."
And they're actually using that to counter
وهم في الواقع يستعملون ذلك للمنافسه
the very large technological edge
مع الافضليه التكنولوجيه الكبيره
that U.S. companies have
التي تملكها الشركات الامريكيه
in areas like the cloud and Internet-based technologies.
في مجالات مثل التخزين الالكتروني و التكنولوجيا المبنيه ىعلى الانترنت.
CA: You're sitting there with the American flag,
كريس : انت تجلس هناك بجوار العلم الامريكي,
and the American Constitution guarantees
والدستور الامريكي يضمن
freedom from unreasonable search and seizure.
الحمايه من التفتيش و الحجز غير القانوني.
How do you characterize
كيف تشخص او تصف
the American citizen's right to privacy?
حق المواطن الامريكي في الخصوصيه؟
Is there such a right?
هل هناك حق للخصوصيه؟
RL: Yeah, of course there is.
ريتشارد: نعم, بالتأكيد.
And we devote an inordinate amount of time and pressure,
ونحن نبذل زمنا و جهدا غير عاديين,
inordinate and appropriate, actually I should say,
غير عادي و مناسب , يجب ان اقول في الحقيقه,
amount of time and effort in order to ensure
نبذل الكثير من الجهد لتأمين و توكيد
that we protect that privacy.
قيامنا بحمايه هذه الخصوصيه.
and beyond that, the privacy of citizens
وخصوصيه المواطنين
around the world, it's not just Americans.
حول العالم, ليس الامر فقط خاصا بالامريكيين.
Several things come into play here.
الكثير من الاشياء موضوعه في الاعتبار هنا.
First, we're all in the same network.
اولا, نحن جميعا في نفس الشبكه.
My communications,
في اتصالاتي,
I'm a user of a particular Internet email service
انا استعمل مخدم بريد الكتروني معين
that is the number one email service of choice
وهو رقم واحد في مخدمي البريد الالكتروني المستعمله من قبل
by terrorists around the world, number one.
الارهابيين حول العالم , رقم واحد.
So I'm there right beside them in email space
لذا انا بجانبهم في ساحات البريد الالكتروني
in the Internet.
في الانترنت
And so we need to be able to pick that apart
لذا نحن بحاجه الى البحث و التدقيق في هذه المساحه
and find the information that's relevant.
و ايجاد المعلومات المفيده لنا.
In doing so, we're going to necessarily encounter
و بقيامنا بهذا, سنقابل بالطبع
Americans and innocent foreign citizens
مواطنين امريكيين و اجانب ابرياء
who are just going about their business,
يقومون باعمالهم العاديه,
and so we have procedures in place that shreds that out,
لذا لدينا خطوات عمل تحمي امثال هؤلاء,
that says, when you find that,
خطوات تقول, عندما تجد هذه المعلومات,
not if you find it, when you find it, because you're certain to find it,
ليس اذا وجدت, عندما تجد , لانك حتما ستجدها,
here's how you protect that.
هذه هي طريقه حمايتها.
These are called minimization procedures.
هذه العمليات تسمى عمليات تحجيم.
They're approved by the attorney general
وهي موافق عليها من قبل المدعي العام
and constitutionally based.
ومبنيه على الدستور.
And so we protect those.
لذا نحن نحمي هذه المعلومات.
And then, for people, citizens of the world
ايضا, للمواطنين حول العالم
who are going about their lawful business
الذين يقومون باعمالهم المشروعه
on a day-to-day basis,
بشكل يومي,
the president on his January 17 speech,
الرئيس الامريكي في خطابه يوم 17 يناير
laid out some additional protections
وضع المزيد من قوانين الحمايه
that we are providing to them.
التي نوفرها لهم.
So I think absolutely,
لذا اعتقد بالاطلاق,
folks do have a right to privacy,
ان للناس حق في الخصوصيه,
and that we work very hard to make sure
ونحن نعمل بجد لتأكيد
that that right to privacy is protected.
ان هذا الحق في الخصوصيه محمي.
CA: What about foreigners using
كريس: ماذا عن استعمال الاجانب
American companies' Internet services?
لخدمات الانترنت المقدمه من الشركات الامريكيه؟
Do they have any privacy rights?
هل لديهم اي حقوق خصوصيه؟
RL: They do. They do, in the sense of,
ريتشارد: لديهم هذه الحقوق ,
the only way that we are able to compel
الطريقه الوحيده التي بامكاننا اقناع
one of those companies to provide us information
واحده من هذه الشركات بتزويدنا بمعلومات
is when it falls into one of three categories:
هي اذا وقعت هذه المعلومات في واحد من ثلاث تصنيفات:
We can identify that this particular person,
يمكننا تحديد ان هذا الشخص تحديدا,
identified by a selector of some kind,
معرفا بعامل اختيار من نوع ما.
is associated with counterterrorist
مرتبط بعمليات ارهاب
or proliferation or other foreign intelligence target.
او تمويل او هدف استخبارات اجنبي.
CA: Much has been made of the fact that
كريس: الكثير تم استقاءه من حقيقه ان
a lot of the information that you've obtained
الكثير من المعلمات التي جمعتموها
through these programs is essentially metadata.
من خلال هذه البرامج هو في الاساس بيانات وصفيه.
It's not necessarily the actual words
هي في الاساس ليست الكلمات الحقيقيه
that someone has written in an email
التي قام شخص ما بكتابتها في رساله
or given on a phone call.
او قالها في مكالمه,
It's who they wrote to and when, and so forth.
انها عن من المرسل اليه و متى , وهكذا.
But it's been argued,
ولكن تم الاحتجاج,
and someone here in the audience has talked
وبعض الجمهور هنا تحدثوا مع
to a former NSA analyst who said
محلل سابق في وكالتكم وقد قال
metadata is actually much more invasive
ان البيانات الوصفيه اكثر تعديا
than the core data,
من البيانات الحقيقيه,
because in the core data
لانه في البيانات الحقيقيه
you present yourself as you want to be presented.
انت تقدم نفسك كما تشاء.
With metadata, who knows what the conclusions are
مع البيانات الوصفيه, لا احد يعلم ما هي التخمينات
that are drawn?
التي تم استقاءها من قبل المراقبين؟
Is there anything to that?
هل من تفسير او رد؟
RL: I don't really understand that argument.
ريتشارد: انا في الواقع لا افهم هذه المغالطه.
I think that metadata's important for a couple of reasons.
اعتقد ان البيانات الوصفيه مهمه لعده اسباب.
Metadata is the information that lets you
البيانات الوصفيه هي المعلومات التي
find connections that people are trying to hide.
تجعلك تجد العلاقات التي يحاول شخص ما اخفاءها.
So when a terrorist is corresponding
لذا عندما يتخابر ارهابي ما
with somebody else who's not known to us
مع شخص اخر ليس معروفا لنا
but is engaged in doing or supporting terrorist activity,
ولكنه متورط في فعل او دعم نشاط ارهابي
or someone who's violating international sanctions
او شخص يخرق المقاطعه الدوليه
by providing nuclear weapons-related material
بتوفير مواد متعلقه بالاسلحه النوويه
to a country like Iran or North Korea,
لدوله مثل ايران او كوريا الشماليه,
is trying to hide that activity because it's illicit activity.
وهو يحاول اخفاء هذا النشاط لانه نشاط غير قانوني.
What metadata lets you do is connect that.
البيانات الوصفيه تسمح لنا الربط بين هذه المعلومات.
The alternative to that
البديل لذلك
is one that's much less efficient
هو بديل اقل كفاءه
and much more invasive of privacy,
و اكثر تعديا على الخصوصيه,
which is gigantic amounts of content collection.
والمتمثل في جمع محتويات هائله الحجم.
So metadata, in that sense,
لذا البيانات الوصفيه, في هذا الاطار,
actually is privacy-enhancing.
هي في الحقيقه داعمه للخصوصيه.
And we don't, contrary to some of the stuff
ونحن لا نقوم , على عكس بعض الاشياء
that's been printed,
التي تم كتابتها عنا,
we don't sit there and grind out
نحن لا نقوم بالجلوس واستخراج
metadata profiles of average people.
بيانات وصفيه لاناس عاديين.
If you're not connected
اذا لم تكن مرتبطا
to one of those valid intelligence targets,
بواحد من هذه الاهداف الاستخباريه المهمه لنا,
you are not of interest to us.
فانت لا تمثل لنا اي اهميه.
CA: So in terms of the threats
كريس: بالنظر الى المهددات
that face America overall,
التي تواجه امريكا عموما,
where would you place terrorism?
اين تضع الارهاب؟
RL: I think terrorism is still number one.
ريتشارد: اعتقد ان الارهاب ما زال هو المهدد الاول.
I think that we have never been in a time
اعتقد انه لم يمر علينا وقت من قبل
where there are more places
تزايدت فيه
where things are going badly
الاماكن غير المستقره, كزماننا هذا
and forming the petri dish in which terrorists
و مشكّله البؤر التي يقوم فيها الارهابيين
take advantage of the lack of governance.
بالاستفاده من غياب الحكم والنظام.
An old boss of mine, Tom Fargo, Admiral Fargo,
احد مدرائي القدماء, توم فارجو . الادميرال فارجو,
used to describe it as arcs of instability.
كان يصف هذه المناطق باقواس عدم النظام,
And so you have a lot of those arcs of instability
لذا لدينا الكثير من هذه المناطق ,
in the world right now,
في العالم الان,
in places like Syria, where there's a civil war
في اماكن مثل سوريا, حيث تجري حرب اهليه
going on and you have massive numbers,
ولدينا ارقام ضخمه
thousands and thousands of foreign fighters
الاف من المقاتلين الاجانب
who are coming into Syria
الذين يدخلون الى سوريا
to learn how to be terrorists
ليتعلموا كيف يصبحون ارهابيين
and practice that activity,
ويتدربو على هذا النشاط,
and lots of those people are Westerners
والكثير من هؤلاء الاشخاص غربيون
who hold passports to European countries
يحملون جوازات لدول اوروبيه
or in some cases the United States,
و في بعض الاحيان الولايات المتحده,
and so they are basically learning how
لذا هم ببساطه يتعلمون كيف
to do jihad and have expressed intent
يقومون بعمليات "جهاد" وقد قاموا بالتعبير عن نيتهم
to go out and do that later on
بالخروج وفعل ذلك لاحقا
in their home countries.
في دولهم التي قدموا منها.
You've got places like Iraq,
لديك اماكن مثل العراق,
which is suffering from a high level of sectarian violence,
التي تعاني من مستوى عالي من العنف الطائفي,
again a breeding ground for terrorism.
ومن جديد تعتبر مرتعا للارهابيين.
And you have the activity in the Horn of Africa
ولديك ايضا النشاط الدائر في القرن الافريقي
and the Sahel area of Africa.
ومنطقه الساحل في افريقيا.
Again, lots of weak governance
مره اخرى, الكثير من الحكومات الضعيفه
which forms a breeding ground for terrorist activity.
التي تشكل ارضيه خصبه للنشاط الارهابي.
So I think it's very serious. I think it's number one.
لذا اعتقد ان الارهاب خطر كبير, اعتقد انه المهدد الاول.
I think number two is cyber threat.
اعتقد ان المهدد الثاني هو التهديد الالكتروني.
I think cyber is a threat in three ways:
اعتقد ان التهديد الاسفيري خطر بثلاث طرق:
One way, and probably the most common way
اول طريق, و غالبا الطريقه الاكثر انتشارا
that people have heard about it,
والكثيرون قد يكونون سمعوا عنها
is due to the theft of intellectual property,
هي نتيجه سرقه المحتوى الادبي,
so basically, foreign countries going in,
ببساطه, دول اجنبيه تدخل,
stealing companies' secrets,
وتقوم بسرقه اسرار شركات,
and then providing that information
وبعدها يقدمون هذه المعلومات
to state-owned enterprises
الى شركات و جهات مملوكه للحكومه
or companies connected to the government
او شركات مرتبطه بالحكومه
to help them leapfrog technology
لمساعدتهم على تسريع عمليه تطوير التكنولوجيا
or to gain business intelligence
او للحصول على استخبارات في مجال الاعمال
that's then used to win contracts overseas.
والتي تستعمل لاحقا للفوز بعقودات خارجيه.
That is a hugely costly set of activities that's going on right now.
هذه حزمه انشطه مكلفه جدا تحدث الان.
Several nation-states are doing it.
والكثير من الدول تقوم بها.
Second is the denial-of-service attacks.
الثاني هو هجمات رفض الخدمه
You're probably aware that there have been
اعتقد انك في الغالب تعرف انه كانت هناك
a spate of those directed against
مجموعه من هذه الهجمات كانت موجهه ضد
the U.S. financial sector since 2012.
القطاع الاقتصادي لامريكا منذ عام 2012.
Again, that's a nation-state who is executing those attacks,
مره اخرى, هذه دول سياديه تقوم بهذه الهجمات,
and they're doing that
وهم يقومون بها
as a semi-anonymous way of reprisal.
كطريقه شبه سريه للانتقام.
And the last one is destructive attacks,
والنوع الاخير هو الهجمات التدميريه,
and those are the ones that concern me the most.
وهذا هو النوع الذي يثير قلقي بالاكثريه.
Those are on the rise.
هذا النوع من الهجمات في تصاعد .
You have the attack against Saudi Aramco in 2012,
لديك الهجوم ضد ارامكو السعوديه عام 2012,
August of 2012.
اغسطس من عام 2012,
It took down about 35,000 of their computers
قد تسبب في تعطيل 35 الف جهاز حاسوب
with a Wiper-style virus.
بفايروس ماسح للبيانات.
You had a follow-on a week later
وكان هناك هجوم لاحق بعدها باسبوع
to a Qatari company.
ضد شركه قطريه
You had March of 2013,
لديك هجوم مارس عام 2013
you had a South Korean attack
لديك هجوم على كوريا الجنوبيه
that was attributed in the press to North Korea
تم اتهام كوريا الشماليه به في الصحافه
that took out thousands of computers.
وقد عطل الاف الحواسيب.
Those are on the rise,
هذا النوع من الهجمات في صعود
and we see people expressing interest
ونرى اناس يعبرون عن اهتمامهم
in those capabilities
بهذه القدرات التخريبيه
and a desire to employ them.
و يعبرن عن رغبه في استخدامها.
CA: Okay, so a couple of things here,
كريس: حسنا, لدي بعض النقاط هنا,
because this is really the core of this, almost.
لان هذا هو في الحقيقه لب الموضوع,
I mean, first of all,
اعني, اولا,
a lot of people who look at risk
الكثيرون الذين ينظرون للمخاطر
and look at the numbers
وينظرون للارقام
don't understand this belief that terrorism
لا يفهمون هذا الايمان ان الارهاب
is still the number one threat.
\ما زال المهدد رقم واحد.
Apart from September 11,
ما عدا هجمات 9/11,
I think the numbers are that in the last 30 or 40 years
اعتقد ان الارقام هي انه في اخر 30-40 سنه
about 500 Americans have died from terrorism,
حوالي 500 امريكي قتلوا في احداث ارهاب,
mostly from homegrown terrorists.
معظمهم من حوادث ارهاب داخلي.
The chance in the last few years
في الاعوام الاخيره, فرصه
of being killed by terrorism
ان يتم قتلك في حادث ارهابي
is far less than the chance of being killed by lightning.
اقل بكثير من فرصه قتلك عن طريق صاعقه.
I guess you would say that a single nuclear incident
اعتقد انه يمكنك قولك ان حادث نووي واحد
or bioterrorism act or something like that
او ارهاب بيولوجي او شيئ من هذا القبيل
would change those numbers.
يمكنه تغيير هذه الارقام.
Would that be the point of view?
هل يمكن ان يكون هذا هو وجهه النظر؟
RL: Well, I'd say two things.
ريتشارد: حسنا, يمكن ان اقول شيئين.
One is, the reason that there hasn't been
اولهما, ان السبب في عدم وجود
a major attack in the United States since 9/11,
حادث ارهابي كبير في امريكا منذ 9/11,
that is not an accident.
هذا ليس صدفه.
That's a lot of hard work that we have done,
هذا بسبب الكثير من العمل الشاق من قبلنا,
that other folks
و من قبل غيرنا
in the intelligence community have done,
في مجتمع الاجهزه الاستخباريه,
that the military has done,
ومن قبل الجيش,
and that our allies around the globe have done.
ومن قبل حلفاءنا حول العالم.
You've heard the numbers about
لقد سمعت الارقام التي
the tip of the iceberg in terms
هي مجرد نقطه ضئيله في بحر المقارنه
of numbers of terrorist attacks that NSA programs
بارقام الهجمات التي قامت الوكاله
contributed to stopping was 54,
بايقافها, هي 54 تهديد,
25 of those in Europe,
25 منها في اوروبا,
and of those 25,
ومن هذه الـ25,
18 of them occurred in three countries,
18 منها حدثت في ثلاث دول ,
some of which are our allies,
بعض منها حلفاءنا,
and some of which are beating the heck out of us
وبعض هذه الدول ينتقدوننا بشده
over the NSA programs, by the way.
حول برنامجنا بالمناسبه.
So that's not an accident that those things happen.
لذا هذه ليست صدفه,
That's hard work. That's us finding intelligence
هذا اجتهاد, هذا ايجادنا للمعلومه الصحيحه
on terrorist activities
حول النشاطات الارهابيه
and interdicting them through one way or another,
وقيامنا باعاقه هذا النشاط بطريقه او باخرى.
through law enforcement,
من خلال السلطات,
through cooperative activities with other countries
من خلال نشاطات تعاونيه مع دول اخرى
and sometimes through military action.
واحيانا من خلال عمليات عسكريه.
The other thing I would say is that
الشيئ الاخر الذي اود قوله هو
your idea of nuclear or chem-bio-threat
فكرتك عن التهديد النووي او البيولوجي
is not at all far-fetched
ليست فكره مبالغ فيها
and in fact there are a number of groups
وفي الحقيقه هناك عده جهات
who have for several years expressed interest
تقوم ولعده سنوات بالتعبير عن اهتمامها
and desire in obtaining those capabilities
ورغبتها في تملك هذه القدرات
and work towards that.
ويعملون من اجل هذا الهدف.
CA: It's also been said that,
كريس: تم ايضا ذكر انه,
of those 54 alleged incidents,
من هذه الهجمات المزعومه الـ54,
that as few as zero of them
ولا واحد منها
were actually anything to do
تم اكتشافه عن طريق
with these controversial programs
هذه البرامج المثيره للجدل
that Mr. Snowden revealed,
التي كشف عنها السيد سنودين,
that it was basically through other forms of intelligence,
ببساطه تم اكتشافها عن طريق وسائل استخباريه اخرى,
that you're looking for a needle in a haystack,
وانك تبحث عن ابره في كوم قش,
and the effects of these programs,
و تأثيرات هذه البرامج ,
these controversial programs,
هذه البرامج المثيره للجدل,
is just to add hay to the stack,
هي فقط لاضافه المزيد من القش للكوم,
not to really find the needle.
وليس للبحث عن الابره.
The needle was found by other methods.
الابره تم ايجادها بوسائل اخرى.
Isn't there something to that?
اليس هناك ما يمكن قوله في هذا الشأن؟
RL: No, there's actually two programs
ريتشارد: لا, هناك في الحقيقه برنامجان
that are typically implicated in that discussion.
يتم عاده تطبيقها في هذا النقاش.
One is the section 215 program,
واحد هو برنامج القطاع 215,
the U.S. telephony metadata program,
برنامج الولايات المتحده للبيانات الوصفيه للاتصال,
and the other one is
والاخر هو
popularly called the PRISM program,
مشهور ببرنامج (بريسم),
and it's actually section 702 of the FISA Amendment Act.
هو في الحقيقه القطاع 702 من تعديل برنامج (فيسا).
But the 215 program
ولكن برنامج 215
is only relevant to threats
له علاقه فقط بالمهددات
that are directed against the United States,
الموجهه ضد الولايات المتحده الامريكيه.
and there have been a dozen threats
وقد كان هناك دسته مهددات
where that was implicated.
تم فيها تطبيق ذلك.
Now what you'll see people say publicly
الجمهور يقول علنا
is there is no "but for" case,
انه ليس هناك حاله "لكن من اجل"
and so there is no case where, but for that,
اي ليس هناك حاله يقال فيها "لكن من اجل" ذلك
the threat would have happened.
كان الهجوم سيقع.
But that actually indicates a lack of understanding
وهذا في الواقع يدل على عدم فهم
of how terrorist investigations actually work.
لكيفيه عمل التحقيقات في حوادث الارهاب.
You think about on television,
انت تعتقد انه في التلفاز مثلا,
you watch a murder mystery.
تشاهد دراما جريمه قتل.
What do you start with? You start with a body,
بماذا يبدأ التحقيق؟ يبدأ بالجثه.
and then they work their way from there to solve the crime.
ومن هناك يعملون لحل الجريمه.
We're actually starting well before that,
نحن نبدأ قبل هذه النقطه في الواقع,
hopefully before there are any bodies,
قبل ان توجد اي جثث,
and we're trying to build the case for
نحن نحاول بناء قضيه
who the people are, what they're trying to do,
لمن هم الاشخاص وماذا يحاولون القيام به,
and that involves massive amounts of information.
وهذا يتضمن كميه هائله من المعلومات.
Think of it is as mosaic,
فكر بها كقطعه فسيفساء,
and it's hard to say that any one piece of a mosaic
من الصعب القول بأن اي قطعه في فسيفساء
was necessary to building the mosaic,
كانت اساسيه لبناء الفسيفساء,
but to build the complete picture,
لكن لبناء الصوره الكامله,
you need to have all the pieces of information.
تحتاج لكل قطع المعلومات.
On the other, the non-U.S.-related threats out of those 54,
ايضا, الهجمات التي لا علاقه لها بامريكا
the other 42 of them,
الهجمات الـ42 الاخرى,
the PRISM program was hugely relevant to that,
برنامج (بريسم) كان محوريا فيها,
and in fact was material in contributing
وكان في الحقيقه اساسيا
to stopping those attacks.
في ايقاف هذه الهجمات.
CA: Snowden said two days ago
كريس: سنودين قال قبل يومين
that terrorism has always been
ان الارهاب كان دائما
what is called in the intelligence world
ما يطلق عليه في عالم الاستخبارات
"a cover for action,"
"غطاء للفعل"
that it's something that,
ان الارهاب شي,
because it invokes such a powerful
لانه يقوم باثاره عاطفه
emotional response in people,
قويه في الناس ,
it allows the initiation of these programs
فانه يسمح باطلاق هذه البرامج
to achieve powers that an organization like yours
للحصول على سلطات لم يكن بامكان منظمات مثل منظمتكم
couldn't otherwise have.
الحصول عليها.
Is there any internal debate about that?
هل هناك اي نقاش داخلي عن هذا؟
RL: Yeah.
ريتشارد: نعم
I mean, we debate these things all the time,
اعني, نحن نتناقش في هذه الاشياء طوال الوقت,
and there is discussion that goes on
وهناك نقاش يدور في
in the executive branch
القطاع التنفيذي
and within NSA itself
وداخل الوكاله نفسها
and the intelligence community about
ومجتمع اجهزه الاستخبارات حول
what's right, what's proportionate,
ما هو الصحيح, ما هو المناسب,
what's the correct thing to do.
ما هو الشيئ الصحيح فعله.
And it's important to note that the programs
ومن المهم ملاحظه ان البرامج
that we're talking about
التي نتحدث عنها
were all authorized by two different presidents,
تم اجازتها من قبل رئيسين مختلفين,
two different political parties,
حزبين سياسيين مختلفين,
by Congress twice,
من قبل الكونجرس مرتين,
and by federal judges 16 different times,
ومن قبل القضاه الفدراليين 16 مره مختلفه,
and so this is not NSA running off
لذا الامر ليس كأن الوكاله تقوم لوحدها
and doing its own thing.
باشياء من نفسها.
This is a legitimate activity
هذه افعال قانونيه
of the United States foreign government
من قبل الذراع الخارجيه للولايات المتحده
that was agreed to by all the branches
وتم الاتفاق عليها من قبل كل القطاعات
of the United States government,
لحكومه الولايات المتحده الامريكيه,
and President Madison would have been proud.
والريس ماديسون كان سيكون فخورا.
CA: And yet, when congressmen discovered
كريس: مع ذلك, عندما اكتشف اعضاء الكونجرس
what was actually being done with that authorization,
ما كان يحدث في الواقع بتلك الصلاحيات,
many of them were completely shocked.
الكثيرون منهم كانوا مصدومين بالكامل.
Or do you think that is not a legitimate reaction,
هل تعتقد ان هذا لم يكن رد فعل حقيقيا,
that it's only because it's now come out publicly,
انه ولان الامر صار علنيا الان,
that they really knew exactly what you were doing
باتوا يعرفون ما تقومون به حقيقه
with the powers they had granted you?
بالصلاحيات التي اعطوها لكم؟
RL: Congress is a big body.
ريتشارد: الكنجرس جسم ضخم.
There's 535 of them,
هناك 535 عضوا,
and they change out frequently,
يتغيرون باستمرار,
in the case of the House, every two years,
مره كل عامين بالنسبه للبرلمان,
and I think that the NSA provided
واعتقد ان الوكاله قدمت
all the relevant information to our oversight committees,
كل المعلومات اللازمه للمجالس الاشرافيه,
and then the dissemination of that information
ونشر هذه المعلومات
by the oversight committees throughout Congress
من قبل اللجنه الاشرافيه عبر الكونجرس
is something that they manage.
هو شيئ يديرونه.
I think I would say that Congress members
اعتقد انني يمكن ان اقول ان اعضاء الكونجرس
had the opportunity to make themselves aware,
كان لديهم الفرصه لتوعيه نفسهم حول الامر,
and in fact a significant number of them,
وفي الحقيقه عدد مقدر منهم,
the ones who are assigned oversight responsibility,
الذين لديهم مهام اشرافيه,
did have the ability to do that.
كان لديهم المقدره لفعل ذلك.
And you've actually had the chairs of those committees say that in public.
وكان لدينا رؤساء هذه اللجان يعترفون بذلك علنا.
CA: Now, you mentioned the threat of cyberattacks,
كريس: الان, انت ذكرت خطر الهجمات الاسفيريه,
and I don't think anyone in this room would disagree
ولا اعتقد ان احدا في هذه الغرفه سيخالفنا
that that is a huge concern,
في اعتقادنا انها مسأله كبيره,
but do you accept that there's a tradeoff
ولكن هل تقبل ان هناك نوع من المتاجره
between offensive and defensive strategies,
بين الاستراتيجيات الدفاعيه و الهجوميه,
and that it's possible that the very measures taken
وانه من المحتمل ان الخطوات التي اتبعت
to, "weaken encryption,"
لاضعاف التشفير
and allow yourself to find the bad guys,
والسماح لانفسكم بايجاد الاشرار,
might also open the door to forms of cyberattack?
يمكن ان تفتح الباب لانواع من الهجمات الاسفيريه؟
RL: So I think two things.
ريتشارد: اعتقد ان هناك امران يمكن قولهما.
One is, you said weaken encryption. I didn't.
الاول, انت قلت اضعاف التشفير, انا لم اقل ذلك.
And the other one is that
والامر الاخر هو
the NSA has both of those missions,
الوكاله لديها المهمتان,
and we are heavily biased towards defense,
ونحن نميل بشده للجانب الدفاعي,
and, actually, the vulnerabilities that we find
وفي الواقع, نقاط الضعف التي نجدها
in the overwhelming majority of cases,
في الغالبيه العظمى من الحالات,
we disclose to the people who are responsible
نقوم باخبار الاشخاص المسؤولين
for manufacturing or developing those products.
عن تصنيع و تطوير هذه المنتجات.
We have a great track record of that,
لدينا سجل جيد في هذا الشأن,
and we're actually working on a proposal right now
ونحن في الواقع نعمل على اقتراح الان
to be transparent and to publish transparency reports
لنكون شفافين و نقدم تقارير شفافيه
in the same way that the Internet companies
بنفس الطريقه التي تقوم شركات الانترنت
are being allowed to publish transparency reports for them.
بنشر تقارير شفافيه عن نفسها.
We want to be more transparent about that.
نريد ان نكون شفافين اكثر حول هذا الامر.
So again, we eat our own dog food.
لذا مره اخرى, نحن نشرب من كأسنا,
We use the standards, we use the products
نستعمل المعايير و نستعمل المنتجات
that we recommend,
التي نوصي بها,
and so it's in our interest
لذا من مصلحتنا
to keep our communications protected
ان نبقي اتصالتنا محميه
in the same way that other people's need to be.
بنفس الطريقه التي يجب حمايه الاخرين بها.
CA: Edward Snowden,
كريس: ادوارد سنودين,
when, after his talk, was wandering the halls here
بعد محادثته وهو يتجول هنا
in the bot,
في الروبوت الخاص به,
and I heard him say to a couple of people,
ولقد سمعته يقول لبضع اشخاص ,
they asked him about what he thought
سألوه عن رأيه
of the NSA overall,
في وكاله الامن القومي المريكيه
and he was very complimentary about the people
وكان مادحا جدا للاشخاص
who work with you,
الذين يعملون معكم
said that it's a really
قال انهم مجموعه
impassioned group of employees
شغوفه من الموظفين
who are seeking to do the right thing,
الذين يعملون من اجل القيام بما هو صحيح.
and that the problems have come from
وان المشكله جاءت من
just some badly conceived policies.
فقط بعض السياسات السيئه.
He came over certainly very reasonably and calmly.
كان يبدوا منطقيا و هادئا.
He didn't come over like a crazy man.
لم يبدوا كأنه شخص مجنون.
Would you accept that at least,
هل تقبل بهذا على الاقل,
even if you disagree with how he did it,
حتى لو كنت مختلفا مع افعاله,
that he has opened a debate that matters?
انه قد فتح باب نقاش مهم؟
RL: So I think that the discussion
ريتشارد: اعتقد ان النقاش
is an important one to have.
هو نقاش مهم.
I do not like the way that he did it.
لا احب الطريقه التي قام بها بالكشف.
I think there were a number of other ways
اعتقد انه كان هناك طرق اخرى
that he could have done that
كان بامكانه اختيارها
that would have not endangered our people
ولم تكن لتسبب الخطر لأناسنا
and the people of other nations
ومواطني الدول الاخرى
through losing visibility
من خلال فقدان الرؤيه
into what our adversaries are doing.
لما يقوم اعداءنا بفعله.
But I do think it's an important conversation.
ولكن اعتقد بانه نقاش مهم.
CA: It's been reported that there's
كريس: تم الحديث عن انه
almost a difference of opinion
هناك عدم اتفاق
with you and your colleagues
بينك و بين زملاءك
over any scenario in which
حول اي سيناريو يمكن فيه
he might be offered an amnesty deal.
منح سنودين عرض عفو.
I think your boss, General Keith Alexander,
اعتقد ان مديرك, جنرال كيث الكساندر,
has said that that would be a terrible example
قال ان ذلك سيكون مثالا سيئا
for others;
للاخرين,
you can't negotiate with someone
لا يمكنك التفاوض
who's broken the law in that way.
مع شخص كسر القوانين.
But you've been quoted as saying that,
ولكن تم اقتباسك وانت تقول,
if Snowden could prove that he was surrendering
لو قام سنودين باثبات انه سيسلم
all undisclosed documents,
كل المعلومات غير المكشوف عنها,
that a deal maybe should be considered.
انه يمكن التفكير في عرض عفو ,
Do you still think that?
كريس: هل ما زلت تعتقد ذلك؟
RL: Yeah, so actually,
ريتشارد: نعم, في الواقع,
this is my favorite thing about that "60 Minutes" interview
كان هذا الجزء المفضل لدي في لقاء (60 دقيقه) الذي اجريته
was all the misquotes that came from that.
كان كل هذه الشائعات التي نتجت عنه.
What I actually said, in response to a question about,
ما قلته في الحقيقه, كرد على سؤال
would you entertain any discussions
هل سترد على اي نقاش
of mitigating action against Snowden,
حول تخفيف العقوبات على سنودين,
I said, yeah, it's worth a conversation.
قلت نعم, يمكن الحديث حل الامر,
This is something that the attorney general
هذا امر قام المدعي العام
of the United States and the president also
للولايات المتحده والرئيس ايضا
actually have both talked about this,
قد تحدثوا عن هذا الامر ,
and I defer to the attorney general,
وانا احيل الامر للمدعي العام,
because this is his lane.
لان هذا اختصاصه.
But there is a strong tradition
لكن هناك تقليد قوي
in American jurisprudence
في العداله الامريكيه
of having discussions with people
للنقاش مع اشخاص
who have been charged with crimes in order to,
تم اتهامهم بتهم, من اجل
if it benefits the government,
في حال كان الامر مفيدا للحكومه
to get something out of that,
للحصول على شئ من هذا الامر,
that there's always room for that kind of discussion.
انه هناك احتماليه لهذا النوع من النقاشات.
So I'm not presupposing any outcome,
لذا انا لا استبق اي نتيجه,
but there is always room for discussion.
ولكن هناك دائما مساحه للنقاش,
CA: To a lay person it seems like
كريس: لشخص عادي يبدوا الامر
he has certain things to offer the U.S.,
كأنه لديه شئ ليقدمه لامريكا,
the government, you, others,
الحكومه, انتم , اخرون,
in terms of putting things right
لوضع الامور في نصابها
and helping figure out a smarter policy,
والمساعده في ايجاد سياسه افضل,
a smarter way forward for the future.
طريقه اذكى للتقدم في المستقبل.
Do you see, has that kind of possibility
هل ترى, هل هذه الاحتماليه
been entertained at all?
تم مناقشتها عموما؟
RL: So that's out of my lane.
ريتشارد: هذا خارج نطاق اختصاصي,
That's not an NSA thing.
هذا لا يخص وكاله الامن القومي,
That would be a Department of Justice
هذا يخص وزاره العدل
sort of discussion.
هذا نقاشهم.
I'll defer to them.
لذا سأحول الامر لهم
CA: Rick, when Ed Snowden ended his talk,
كريس: عندما انهى ادوارد سنودين محادثته,
I offered him the chance to share an idea worth spreading.
منحته فرصه مشاركه فكره تستحق الانتشار.
What would be your idea worth spreading
ما هي فكرتك التي تستحق الانتشار
for this group?
لهذه المجموعه؟
RL: So I think, learn the facts.
ريتشارد: اعتقد انها , اعرف الحقائق.
This is a really important conversation,
هذه مناقشه مهمه,
and it impacts, it's not just NSA,
وتأثيرها, ليس فقط على الوكاله,
it's not just the government,
ليس فقط على الحكومه,
it's you, it's the Internet companies.
تأثيرها عليك انت, على شركات الانترنت,
The issue of privacy and personal data
قضيه الخصوصيه و البيانات الشخصيه
is much bigger than just the government,
اكبر من مجرد الحكومه,
and so learn the facts.
لذا اعرفوا الحقائق.
Don't rely on headlines,
لا تعتمدوا على رؤوس العناوين,
don't rely on sound bites,
لا تعتمدو على الملخصات,
don't rely on one-sided conversations.
لا تعتمدوا على النقاشات الاحاديه,
So that's the idea, I think, worth spreading.
لذا هذه فكره اعتقد انها تستحق الانتشار.
We have a sign, a badge tab,
لدينا في العمل بطاقات,
we wear badges at work with lanyards,
نلبس بطاقات في العمل عليها اشارات,
and if I could make a plug,
وان كان بامكاني عمل اضافه,
my badge lanyard at work says, "Dallas Cowboys."
اشاره بطاقتي في العمل مكتوب عليها :(دالاس كاوبويس)
Go Dallas.
اشجع هذا الفريق.
I've just alienated half the audience, I know.
لقد اغضبت نصف الحضور الان , اعرف.
So the lanyard that our people
لذا الاشاره التي
who work in the organization
يلبسها اعضاء الفريق
that does our crypto-analytic work
الذين يقومون باعمال تحليل التشفير
have a tab that says, "Look at the data."
الاشاره مكتوب عليها : "انظر للبيانات"
So that's the idea worth spreading.
هذه هي الفكره التي تستحق الانتشار
Look at the data.
انظر للبيانات.
CA: Rick, it took a certain amount of courage,
كريس: ريتشارد, هذا فعل شجاع
I think, actually, to come and speak openly
من قبلكم , ان تأتوا وتتحدثوا
to this group.
مع هذه المجموعه بكل صراحه
It's not something the NSA has done a lot of in the past,
هذا ليس امرا قامت الوكاله بفعله في السابق,
and plus the technology has been challenging.
و نعتذر عن المشاكل التقنيه .
We truly appreciate you doing that
نحن ممتنون لقيامك بهذا
and sharing in this very important conversation.
ومشاركتك لنا في هذا الحوار المهم.
Thank you so much.
شكرا جزيلا لك.
RL: Thanks, Chris.
ريتشارد: شكرا كريس